and that hangar could just fit the Statue of Liberty in it, so you get a sense of size of that Falcon Heavy Rocket. CA: And the fact that there are 27 engines there. That's part of the design principle that you, rather than just inventing ever bigger rockets, you team them up. GS: It's exactly this residual capability. We developed the Merlin engine for the Falcon 1 launch vehicle. We could have tossed that engine and built an entirely new engine for the Falcon 9. It would have been called something different, because Falcon 9 is nine Merlin engines, but instead of spending a billion dollars on a brand new engine, we put nine of them together on the back end of Falcon 9. Residual capability: glue three Falcon 9s together and you have the largest operational rocket flying. And so it was expensive to do, but it was a much more efficient path than starting from scratch. CA: And the BFR is the equivalent of how much bigger than that, in terms of its power? GS: BFR is about, I believe, two and half times the size of this. CA: Right, and so that allows you -- I mean, I still don't really believe this video that we're about to play here. What on earth is this? GS: So it currently is on earth, but this is basically space travel for earthlings. I can't wait for this residual capability. Basically, what we're going to do is we're going to fly BFR like an aircraft and do point-to-point travel on earth, so you can take off from New York City or Vancouver and fly halfway across the globe. You'll be on the BFR for roughly half an hour or 40 minutes, and the longest part -- yeah, it's so awesome. (Applause) The longest part of that flight is actually the boat out and back. (Laughter) CA: I mean. Gwynne, come on, this is awesome, but it's crazy, right? This is never going to actually happen. GS: Oh no, it's definitely going to happen. This is definitely going to happen. CA: How? (Applause) So first of all, countries are going to accept this incoming missile -- (Laughter) GS: Chris, so can you imagine us trying to convince a federal range, Air Force bases to take the incomers? Because we're doing it now, regularly, right? We're bringing the first stages back, and we're landing them on federal property on an Air Force base. So I think doing it, I don't know, 10 kilometers out from a city, maybe it's only five kilometers out from a city. CA: So how many passengers can possibly afford the fortune of flying by space? GS: So the first BFR is going to have roughly a hundred passengers. And let's talk a little bit about the business. Everyone thinks rockets are really expensive, and to a large degree they are, and how could we possibly compete with airline tickets here? But if you think about it, if I can do this trip in half an hour to an hour, I can do dozens of these a day, right? And yet, a long-haul aircraft can only make one of those flights a day. So even if my rocket was slightly more expensive and the fuel is a little bit more expensive, I can run 10x at least what they're running in a day, and really make the revenue that I need to out of that system. CA: So you really believe this is going to be deployed at some point in our amazing future. When? GS: Within a decade, for sure. CA: And this is Gwynne time or Elon time? GS: That's Gwynne time. I'm sure Elon will want us to go faster. (Laughter) CA: OK, that's certainly amazing. GS: I'm personally invested in this one, because I travel a lot and I do not love to travel, and I would love to get to see my customers in Riyadh, leave in the morning and be back in time to make dinner. CA: So we're going to test this out. So within 10 years, an economy price ticket, or, like, a couple thousand dollars per person to fly New York to Shanghai. GS: Yeah, I think it'll be between economy and business, but you do it in an hour. CA: Yeah, well, OK, that is definitely something. (Laughter) And meanwhile, the other use of BFR is being developed to go a little bit further than Shanghai. Talk about this. You guys have actually developed quite a detailed, sort of, picture of how humans might fly to Mars, and what that would look like. GS: Yeah. So we've got a video, this is a cropped video from others we've shown, and then there's a couple of new bits to it. But basically, you're going to lift off from a pad, you've got a booster as well as the BFS, the Big Falcon Spaceship. It's going to take off. The booster is going to drop the spaceship off in orbit, low earth orbit, and then return just like we're returning boosters right now. So it sounds incredible, but we're working on the pieces, and you can see us achieve these pieces. So booster comes back. The new thing here is that we're going to actually land on the pad that we launched from. Currently, we land on a separate pad, or we land out on a boat. Fast, quick connect. You take a cargo ship full of fuel, or a fuel depot, put it on that booster, get that in orbit, do a docking maneuver, refuel the spaceship, and head on to your destination, and this one is Mars. CA: So, like, a hundred people go to Mars at one time, taking, what, six months? Two months? GS: It ends up depending on how big the rocket is. I think this first version, and we'll continue to make even bigger BFRs, I think it's a three-month trip. Right now, the average is six to eight, but we're going to try to do it faster. CA: When do you believe SpaceX will land the first human on Mars? GS: It's a very similar time frame from the point-to-point. It's the same capability. It will be within a decade -- not this decade. CA: In real time, again, within a decade. Well, that would also be amazing. (Laughter) Why, though? Seriously, why? I mean, you've got a company where this is the official stated mission. Has everyone actually bought into that mission, given that, I mean, there's a lot of people around who think, come on, you've got so much talent, so much technology capability. There are so many things on earth that need urgent attention. Why would you have this escape trip off to another planet? (Applause) GS: So I am glad you asked that, but I think we need to expand our minds a little bit. There are plenty of things to do on earth, but there are lots of companies working on that. I think we're working on one of the most important things we possibly can, and that's to find another place for humans to live and survive and thrive. If something happened on earth, you need humans living somewhere else. (Applause) It's the fundamental risk reduction for the human species. And this does not subvert making our planet here better and doing a better job taking care of it, but I think you need multiple paths to survival, and this is one of them. And let's not talk about the downer piece, like, you go to Mars to make sure all earthlings don't die. That's terrible, actually, that's a terrible reason to go do it. Fundamentally, it's another place to explore, and that's what makes humans different from animals, it's our sense of exploration and sense of wonderment and learning something new. And then I also have to say, this is the first step in us moving to other solar systems and potentially other galaxies, and I think this is the only time I ever out-vision Elon, because I want to meet other people in other solar systems. Mars is fine, but it is a fixer-upper planet. There's work to do there to make it habitable. (Laughter) I want to find people, or whatever they call themselves, in another solar system. CA: That is a big vision. Gwynne Shotwell, thank you. You have one of the most amazing jobs on the planet. GS: Thank you very much. Thanks, Chris.
y en ese hangar podría caber la Estatua de la Libertad, para tener una idea del tamaño de ese Falcon Heavy Rocket. CA: Y el hecho de que hay 27 motores allí. Eso es parte del principio de diseño que en lugar de inventar cohetes cada vez más grandes, uno pueda unirlos. GS: Es exactamente esta capacidad residual. Desarrollamos el motor Merlin para el vehículo de lanzamiento Falcon 1. Podríamos haber arrojado ese motor y construir un motor completamente nuevo para el Falcon 9. Se habría denominado algo diferente, porque Falcon 9 es nueve motores Merlin, pero en lugar de gastar USD 1000 millones en un nuevo motor, ponemos nueve de ellos juntos en la parte trasera de Falcon 9. Capacidad residual: pegue tres Falcon 9 juntos y se obtiene el mayor cohete operacional volando. Y fue costoso de hacer, pero fue un camino mucho más eficiente que comenzar desde cero. CA: Y el BFR es el equivalente a ¿cuánto más grande que eso, en términos de su poder? GS: BFR es aproximadamente, creo, dos veces y media más grande. CA: Correcto, y eso te permite ... Quiero decir, no me creo este video que estamos a punto de ver aquí. ¿Qué es esto? GS: Actualmente está en la Tierra, pero esto es básicamente un viaje espacial para los terrícolas. No puedo esperar a esta capacidad residual. Básicamente, lo que vamos a hacer es volar BFR como un avión y hacer viajes punto a punto en la Tierra, para que pueda despegar desde la ciudad de Nueva York o Vancouver y volar a la mitad del globo. Estarás en el BFR durante una media hora o 40 minutos, y la parte más larga... sí, es tan increíble. (Aplausos) La parte más larga de ese vuelo es el bote hacia afuera y hacia atrás. (Risas) CA: Gwynne, vamos, esto es increíble, pero es una locura, ¿no? Esto nunca va a suceder realmente. GS: Oh sí, definitivamente va a suceder. Esto definitivamente va a suceder. CA: ¿Cómo? (Aplausos) En primer lugar, los países aceptarán este misil entrante... (Risas) GS: Chris, ¿te imaginas tratando de convencer a nivel federal, bases de la Fuerza Aérea para aceptar los entrantes? Porque lo estamos haciendo ya, regularmente. Estamos trayendo las primeras etapas, y aterrizamos en una propiedad federal, bases de la Fuerza Aérea. Entonces creo que hacerlo, no sé, a 10 km de una ciudad, tal vez solo esté a 5 km de una ciudad. CA: ¿Cuántos pasajeros pueden permitirse la fortuna de volar por el espacio? GS: El primer BFR tendrá unos cien pasajeros. Y hablemos un poco sobre el negocio. Todos piensan que los cohetes son realmente caros, y en gran medida lo son, y ¿cómo podríamos competir con los boletos de avión aquí? Pero si lo piensas bien, si puedo hacer este viaje en media hora a una hora, puedo hacer docenas de estos al día, ¿verdad? Y un avión de largo recorrido solo puede hacer uno de esos vuelos al día. Así que incluso si mi cohete fuera un poco más caro y el combustible es un poco más caro, puedo ejecutar 10 veces lo que están ejecutando en un día, y realmente hacer que los ingresos que necesito salgan de ese sistema. CA: Realmente crees que esto se implementará en algún momento en nuestro increíble futuro ¿Cuándo? GS: Dentro de una década, seguro. CA: ¿Y este es tiempo Gwynne o tiempo Elon? CA: Es tiempo Gwynne. Estoy segura de que Elon querrá que vayamos más rápido. (Risas) CA: Eso es ciertamente sorprendente. GS: Personalmente he invertido en esto, porque viajo mucho y no me gusta viajar, y me encantaría ver a mis clientes en Riyadh, salir por la mañana y regresar a tiempo para preparar la cena. CA: Entonces vamos a probar esto. Dentro de 10 años, el precio de un boleto de segunda por persona será de un par de miles de dólares para volar de Nueva York a Shanghái. GS: Sí, creo que será boleto de segunda y primera, pero se hará en una hora. CA: Sí, bueno, está bien, definitivamente es algo. (Risas) Y mientras tanto, el otro uso de BFR que se está desarrollando es ir un poco más allá que Shanghái. Habla de esto. Uds. han desarrollado algo bastante detallado, una especie de imagen de cómo los humanos podrían volar a Marte, y cómo se vería eso. GS: Sí. Tenemos un video, este es un video recortado de otros que hemos mostrado, y hay un par de cosas nuevas. Pero, básicamente, se despega de una plataforma, con un cohete, así como BFS, la nave espacial Big Falcon. Va a despegar. El cohete va a dejar la nave espacial en órbita órbita terrestre baja, y luego regresa al igual que devolvemos los cohetes en este momento. Suena increíble, pero estamos trabajando en las piezas, y puedes vernos lograr estas piezas. Así que el cohete vuelve. Lo nuevo aquí es que aterrizaremos en la plataforma desde la que la lanzamos. Actualmente aterrizamos en una plataforma separada o en un bote. Conexión rápida y veloz. Tomas un buque de carga lleno de combustible, o un depósito de combustible, se pone en el cohete, se pone en órbita, hace una maniobra de atraque, reposta la nave espacial, y se dirige a su destino, y este es Marte. CA: Entonces, cien personas van a Marte al mismo tiempo, y lleva qué, ¿seis meses? ¿Dos meses? GS: Termina dependiendo de lo grande que sea el cohete. Creo que esta primera versión, y seguiremos haciendo incluso mayores que el BFR. Creo que es un viaje de tres meses. En este momento, el promedio es de seis a ocho, pero vamos a tratar de hacerlo más rápido. CA: ¿Cuándo crees que SpaceX aterrizará al primer humano en Marte? GS: Es un marco de tiempo muy similar al punto a punto. Es la misma capacidad. Será en una década, no en esta década. CA: En tiempo real, nuevamente, dentro de una década. Eso también sería increíble. (Risas) ¿Pero por qué? ¿En serio, por qué? Quiero decir, existe esa empresa con esa la misión oficial declarada. ¿Han comprado todos esa misión dado que, hay mucha gente que piensa, tienen mucho talento, y mucha capacidad tecnológica. Y hay muchas cosas en la Tierra que necesitan atención urgente. ¿Por qué tienen ese viaje de escape a otro planeta en mente? (Aplausos) GS: Me alegra que me hayas preguntado eso, pero creo que tenemos que expandir nuestras mentes un poco. Hay muchas cosas que hacer en la Tierra, pero hay muchas compañías trabajando en eso. Creo que trabajamos en una de las cosas más importantes que podemos, y eso es encontrar otro lugar para que los humanos vivan, sobrevivan y prosperen. Si algo sucediera en la Tierra, los humanos deben vivir en otro lado. (Aplausos) Es la reducción de riesgo fundamental para la especie humana. Y esto no subvierte hacer que nuestro planeta aquí sea mejor y hacer un mejor trabajo para cuidarlo, pero creo que se necesitan múltiples caminos para sobrevivir, Y este es uno de ellos. Y no hablemos de la pieza deprimente, como, vas a Marte para asegurarte de que todos los terrícolas no mueran. Eso es terrible, de hecho, esa es una razón terrible para hacerlo. Fundamentalmente, es otro lugar para explorar, y eso es lo que hace a los humanos diferentes de los animales, es nuestro sentido de exploración y sentido de asombro y aprender algo nuevo. Y luego también tengo que decir, este es el primer paso moviéndonos a otros sistemas solares y potencialmente otras galaxias, y creo que esta es la única vez que sobrepaso la visión de Elon, porque quiero conocer otras personas en otros sistemas solares. Marte está bien, pero necesita arreglo. Hay trabajo que hacer allí para hacerlo habitable. (Risas) Quiero encontrar personas o como se llamen, en otro sistema solar. CA: Esa es una gran visión. Gwynne Shotwell, gracias. Tienes uno de los trabajos más increíbles del planeta. GS: Muchas gracias. Gracias, Chris.